software engineering radio episode 17 listener feedback and roadmap
hello everybody to this short meta episode on software engineering radio I'll cover some listener feedback as well as an outlook on what the upcoming topics
and interviews will be so let's first take a look at the upcoming regular episodes the next episode will probably be the resource management
episode where mcil Hill talks together with his colleague Prashant Jane about their book on resource management patterns it's
actually posed our three pattern oriented software architecture volume three it's about things such as activation deactivation
and lifecycle management of potentially expensive resources after
that we'll come up with part two of the concurrency series whether we'll have a number three episode on concurrency depends someone on your feedback
and on the download numbers the download numbers for concurrency one haven't been that great
so if they're also not that great for concurrency part two
we might even skip concurrency part three a very important upcoming topic will be software architecture in general
we will record three or four episodes on this topic episode 1 for architecture has already recorded
and it contains basically definitions and fundamentals of software architecture
and we'll continue with this topic things like documenting software architectures
and also how to make sure a software architecture is efficiently implemented in large teams we've also recorded the exception handling episode
which will be basically the sequel to the error handling episode we had earlier
and we're also working on an episode about typing to clarify some of the issues with regards to
you know what compilers will do while runtime typing is what duck typing is
and also how this plays into compiled versus dynamically interpreted scripting languages we're also working on a series of episodes on
service-oriented architecture as a way it's going to be a three part episode episode one on this topic will be an episode mainly by a bahut
who talks about the business
and non-technical aspects of SOA will then look at some implementation details of SOA
we take a look at some of the technologies such as jbi
and SCA and also maybe some of the web services stuff part three will be somewhat critical view of SOA to take a
look at the real world challenges another interesting topic that we'll have coming up is variabilities how do you manage variabilities in software systems
and that will lead us to a very interesting topic that will get some attention which can also be seen as some kind of architecture related thing
which is a product line engineering another thing we're going to take on in the future rather soon is software
development processes we will have one episode about fundamentals like what's the difference between waterfall agile
and all that stuff and we'll also have an episode where we will talk to people
who have somewhat more formal or stringent requirements to the development process specifically in the medical area
so now you know what's coming up in the regular episodes if you want additional stuff
if you have additional recommendations what we should cover please let us know
and send us an email at team @ s e - radio dotnet
or add a comment to our website at se - radio dotnet comments are always better
because other people can see what you're thinking we also have a couple of interesting interviews coming up one
that we have already recalled it is with Utah Eckstein she's an expert in agile software development and specifically in applying agile software development in large projects
so this is going to be really interesting another interview we have also already recorded is with my co-star he's also one of the original poser authors
and he'll talk about middleware and also to some extent about architecture
and also on j2ee versus dotnet another interview we've already recorded is with James Noble it's a rather short interview
and it's about postmodern software development another interview topic we're working on is we're trying to get
somebody from NASA on the mic to talk to us about development of software for the International Space Station and/or the Space Shuttle to understand more about
the requirement the challenges and the limitations of software development for safety critical systems that run in hazardous environment such as in space
where you have all those radiation problems we are tryin T trying to dig our way through NASA we've talked to the public relations people
and let's see how this turns out it's not I would say it's not yet completely a hundred percent sure
that this is going to really materialize we also have a number of additional interesting interview candidates on the line
but as I said before I'm not going to announce any names unless we actually recorded the interview
because finding a suitable time slot can be challenging so let's get to some of the listener feedback we received over the last I don't know one
or two months we received several emails that basically said that what we do is great
and that we should continue and that we have a good as one listener pointed out a good signal to noise ratio
so we kind of managed to pack a lot of information into this relatively constrained period of time
although some even say that our podcasts are too long so thanks for all the positive feedback it's really encouraging to see
that people actually like would like what we do we're not going to read all those emails that say that we're doing good work because I mean yeah it's it's very good for us and we really like those emails
and please keep sending them or better yet at comments to the to the page to the webpage but we're not going to read them
so let's take a look at the more specific things people mentioned one thing or actually a couple of things
that Michelle Hummer suggested were there should be an episode on refactoring which is absolutely true will will do
that we'll we'll have an episode on refactoring basics
and also one on refactoring in larger projects
then another thing he suggested was an episode about programming against interfaces why this is why this is
specifically important so you
know being able to exchange implementations to use mock objects to be able to wrap everything behind facades to add
decorators to add proxies what we'll also do some time in the future based on a recommendation or an idea from here is to come up with an episode
where we recommend good books that we have read and where we think that you should read them too so a book recommendation episode will be something
that we'll probably do during summer time when all of us don't have too much time producing real contents
that we'll come up with this book recommendation thing another thing
that behaves just it was taking a look at things like build tools build process and so on and yes we'll cover
that probably the problem is we don't want to make this too specific for specific environment right I mean we don't want to do an episode about maven
or ant so finding somebody who can talk about build processes in general while not explaining a specific tool is probably a challenge
and we don't have the right handle on that yet there was another thing we had suggested
and that was to have transcriptions of our podcasts
so basically having textual copies of what we say in the episodes
now actually this is a lot of work and we don't have our scripts prepared in a way that we could publish them as transcripts
so probably what we'd have to do is to listen to what we talked in the episodes and then write things down
and this is actually a lot of work which we won't be able to do it's a lot of work already to produce the podcast and we probably don't have the time to produce transcripts however
if there is somebody who wants to you know like I don't know join the team or or help us
or I don't know get famous by producing those transcripts that would certainly be a great thing
and we'll obviously be hosting them on our website
so if you have spare time and want to contribute to this podcast by producing the transcripts let us know we'll find a way to arrange
that so here is an excerpt of an email sent by Bob Savage he says I haven't caught up with the show
yet completely but after listening to both the scripting languages episode
and the listener comment in episode 9 about static versus dynamic typing
I would really like to hear your response to some comments made by guido van rossum in a speech recorded at Xerox PARC the speech is available in two
parts from the software development forum podcast
which is hosted by IT conversations the basic idea is compiler type checking isn't as useful as people think
because 99 out of 100 bucks that show up in the field are unexpected values such as null values negative integers feeds vs. meters etc
which are not caught by typical specifically referring Java type systems he stresses
the importance of unit tests so we'll certainly cover or try to address this topic in our typing episode
so that should be I don't know within the next seven or eight episodes we'll we'll cover this topic in detail something
that a couple of people suggested was to take a look at software development tooling specifically IDE s I'm not sure
that we're going to do that I mean I don't think
that IDs are kind of in the center of what our podcast is all about the same is true for for other tools
like ant or maven or j-unit because there again very specific to a certain platform in this case Java what
we will definitely do is take a look at the concepts behind those tools like for
example testing concept behind j-unit unit testing mock objects
or things like dependency analysis architectural analysis that's certainly something
we'll do but I don't think we'll talk too much about very specific tooling except as
I said as an example of a broader category of things that we want to talk about
so here's a comment posted by Marc Garneau he's actually the editor of cogeneration net you might want to take a look at it
if you think cogeneration is interesting
and he says thanks for another very good discussion it was interesting to hear about a move away from Java towards ruby by some classes of developers it's also worth
noting that lisp has had many of the features mentioned in ruby for many years now macros give the ability to implement their own specific languages
that can themselves be tightly integrated with the base Lizz language and this is a very commonly used technique a common list object system offers mix-ins
and runtime changes to the class hierarchy including class redefinition addition removal of methods at etc
and a powerful meta programming model may be the next move will be from ruby to lisp form
or ruby you could see our interview with Dave Thomas on the code generation network Tom the guy who was part of the Ruby
and practice episode to which Mark added the comment replied as follows mark thank you for the kind words I agree with you
that today more people consider using high-level programming languages again that have been around for a while Lisbon Smalltalk probably set the standards
but new languages are trying to catch up however if you listen carefully I do not have to advocate
and move away from Java the platform is just too valuable I rather welcome the JS are 223
and Springs approach to incorporate scripting languages onto the Java VM so another comment I want to add to this discussion
if you think or if you interested in learning how Lisp
and C lost the Common Lisp object system implement those DSL constructs there is a book
that we mentioned somewhere in the show notes before which is called the out of the metal object protocol by Craig or catch Alice and a couple of other people
and this book explains nicely all those fancy ways of creating your own dia cells will also add an episode on Lisp
and C laws and meta programming sometime later because I personally think this is a fascinating topic although I never used it in practice
so I think this completes the listener feedback
and this also completes this quite short episode see
you or hear you next time thanks bye
[Music]
this was another episode of software engineering radio the software engineering radio team wants to thank Henning poly for providing the music as well as lips
and comm for hosting in bandwidth for more information on the podcast past episodes and feedback go to s e - radio dotnet
[Music]